<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A necessary treatise for this age, or, A plain discovery of that great error of denying baptisme with water to the children of believers in justification of the arguments of John Turner, for infants basptisme, against Robert Admond : together with several other useful particulars on this subject, the contents whereof follow in the next page / briefly and plainly handled and discust by Thomas Wall.</title>
            <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1669</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 94 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 27 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A67325</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W486</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R38029</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">17162031</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 17162031</idno>
            <idno type="VID">106057</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A67325)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 106057)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1624:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A necessary treatise for this age, or, A plain discovery of that great error of denying baptisme with water to the children of believers in justification of the arguments of John Turner, for infants basptisme, against Robert Admond : together with several other useful particulars on this subject, the contents whereof follow in the next page / briefly and plainly handled and discust by Thomas Wall.</title>
                  <author>Wall, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>51 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed fro Tho. Wall and Barn. Frencham, and are to be sold by Nath. Crouch ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1669.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Turner, John, b. 1649 or 50. --  Vindication of infant baptism.</term>
               <term>Infant baptism --  Apologetic works.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:106057:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A Neceſſary TREATISE for this Age OR, A Plain diſcovery of that great Error of denying Baptiſme with Water to the Children of Believers.</p>
            <p>In juſtification of the Arguments of <hi>John Turner,</hi> for Infants Baptiſme, againſt <hi>Robert Admond.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Together with ſeveral other uſeful particulars on this Subject, the Contents whereof follow in the next Page.</p>
            <p>Briefly, and plainly handled and diſcuſt by <hi>THOMAS WALL.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>
               <bibl>Luke 18. 16.</bibl> Suffer little Children to come unto me, and forbid them not, for of ſuch is the Kingdom of God.</q>
            <q>
               <bibl>Acts 2. 39.</bibl> For the Promiſe is to you and your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, &amp;c. <hi>Acts 16. 15.</hi> And when ſhe was Baptiſed and her houſhold, &amp;c.</q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>Tho. Wall,</hi> and <hi>Barn. Frencham,</hi> and are to beſold by <hi>Nath. Crouc<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> at the <hi>Croſs-Keyes</hi> in <hi>Biſhopſgate-ſtreet,</hi> near <hi>Leaden-Hall.</hi> 1669.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="table_of_contents">
            <pb facs="tcp:106057:2"/>
            <head>The Contents.</head>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>A</hi> Plain diſcovery of that great Error of deny<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Infants Baptiſm with water to the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of Believers.</item>
               <item>2. <hi>John Turners</hi> Argument for Infants Baptiſm ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified.</item>
               <item>3. A deſoription of the ſtate of Infants as they come from <hi>Adams</hi> loyns.</item>
               <item>4. What Chriſts ſpiritual bleſſing was on the Infants brought to him, the want they had of it, and benefit received by it, and by it they had right to Baptiſme of water.</item>
               <item>5. That a mans children are his houſhold.</item>
               <item>6. That Believers children were Baptiſed by the hands of the Apoſtles.</item>
               <item>7. The word Baptiſme opened by context of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</item>
               <item>8. Who are the true Adminiſtrators of Baptiſme.</item>
               <item>9. Where it ought to be done.</item>
               <item>10. On what part of the body it ought to be admini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtred.</item>
               <item>11. That the <hi>Anabaptiſts</hi> according to their own judgment are not yet Baptiſed.</item>
               <item>12. That the Baptiſm received in Apoſtate Churches, ought not to be reiterated.</item>
            </list>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:106057:2"/>
            <head>The Preface to the Reader, concerning the occaſion of this Treatiſe.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>I. T.</hi> that worthy Souldier of Jeſus Chriſt, about 12 years ago, delivered his Judgment in a Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon from <hi>1 Cor. 10. 1<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. verſes,</hi> Proving from thence the lawfulneſs of Infants Baptiſm; One that heard him, took the ſum of the matter delivered in writing, and gave it to <hi>R. A.</hi> who made ſome Anſwer to <hi>J. T</hi>'s. Doctrine, and ſent it to him: In anſwer to which wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting of <hi>R<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> A. J. T.</hi> framed this Argument in the beginning of this Treatiſe; and to the Argument <hi>R. A.</hi> made ſome farther Anſwer. <hi>R. A.</hi> ſhewing me the writings of both ſides, I having well conſidered the matter, and diſcerned much wait in <hi>J. T</hi>'s. Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and <hi>R. A</hi>'s. grant to the ſame: And <hi>J. T.</hi> being aged, and weakned much in body, by reaſon of his long (nigh 14 years) impriſonment for the Cauſe of Chriſt, and after that a long time of ſickneſs, was not forward to trouble himſelf with Controverſies in his latter dayes, but to imploy himſelf in more comfortable Meditati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: I thought my ſelf bound in duty, having received a Talent of the Lord, and ought not to hide it in the earth, <hi>Matth. 25. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>8, 27.</hi> the Harveſt being ſo great, and they that are faithful Labourers ſo few, and the truth of God ſo much in theſe our dayes decayed, I could not forbear, but ſet the trump of Gods Word to my mouth to vindicate this bleſſed Truth of the Lord, of the Right that the Infants of Believers have to Baptiſm of water, <hi>Iſa. 59. 19.</hi> though the Enemy ſhall come in like a Flood for the ſame, but the Lord is the ſtrength of my Life, of whom ſhall I be afraid, <hi>Pſal. 27. 1.</hi> Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidering, if it were poſſible, to reclaim my friend <hi>R. A.</hi> from his error, I ſent to him the tenor of this enſuing Treatiſe, which remained with him about a year and
<pb facs="tcp:106057:3"/> half, expecting his approving or diſproving of the ſame: A friend of mine, underſtanding what I had wrote <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired to ſee it, much deſiring me to put it to publick view, for ſome Reaſons; Firſt, Becauſe the truth of Infants Baptiſm ſo plainly manifeſted, is ſo needful to come abroad. Secondly, Becauſe ſo many poyſoned Books in denying Infants Baptiſm, are ſpread abroad. Thirdly, The many thouſands of people that are led a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way in the error of the ſame; the Cap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain of this, and other Errors, was one<note place="margin">Of this Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> is more ſpoken in this treatis worth noting.</note> 
               <hi>Smith,</hi> who Baptiſed himſelf, being once a ſeeming Member of a true Church in <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> where Mr. <hi>Henry Ainſworth</hi> at that time was Teacher, but for Error Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> was caſt out which was as the Star called Wormwood, which fell upon the third part of the Rivers, and upon the Fountains of waters, and many men dyed of the Waters becauſe they were made bitter, <hi>Rev. 8. 10, 11.</hi> but the waters of Gods truths, being pure water of Life, clear as Cryſtal, <hi>Rev. 22. 1.</hi> which make glad the City of God, <hi>Pſal. 46. 4.</hi> but falſe Shepheards and evil Teachers do foul and muddy the waters of Gods Truth with their feet, <hi>Ezek. 34. 18, 19.</hi> So that bit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terneſs ſpringeth up to trouble the faithful, <hi>Heb. 12. 15.</hi> With their Tongues they have uſed deceit, <hi>Rom. 3. 13.</hi> And lye in wait to deceive, <hi>Epheſ. 4. 14.</hi> What need then hath every Soul to ſearch the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures daily, <hi>Acts 17. 11.</hi> Believing no mans Opinion of Scripture, unleſs it be ſo underſtood, that the Old and New Teſtament may agree in one harmony together, and then he or ſhe ſhall go on in ſafety, which is the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire of him who is thine in all Chriſtian duty.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Tho. Wall.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:106057:3"/>
            <head>
               <hi>John Turners</hi> Argument for Infants Baptiſm <hi>Verbatim,</hi> ſent to <hi>Robert Admands.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>THey that Chriſt bleſſed with a ſpiritual bleſſing, had right to Baptiſm of Water.</p>
            <p>Little Children held in Arms, had right to Baptiſm of Water, becauſe Chriſt bleſſed them with a Spiritual bleſſing.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. A's.</hi> Anſwer to <hi>J. T's. Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And grant is, That the Infants bleſt by Chriſt, were bleſſed with a ſpiritual bleſſing, with this de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyal,</p>
            <p>That thoſe Infants which Chriſt bleſſed with a Spiritual Bleſſing, had no right to Baptiſm of Water.</p>
            <p>Tho. Wall'<hi>s Reply to</hi> R. A'<hi>s Anſwer of</hi> J. T'<hi>s. Argument.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Foraſmuch as you grant, that thoſe Children held in Arms, and brought to Chriſt, were bleſſed with a Spiritual bleſſing, it is then needful to examine by the golden Reed of Gods written Word, what this ſpiritual bleſſing was, the neceſſity the Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren had of it, the benefit they received by it, and that by partaking of it, they had right to Baptiſm of Water; ſo I ſhall begin in order with the firſt particular; That is,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>What this Spiritual bleſſing was Chriſt beſtowed on thoſe Infants brought to him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Evangeliſt <hi>Luke</hi> is a true expounder what Chriſt Spiritual was, as it is written, <hi>Ye are the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of the Prophets, and of the Covenant which God made with our Fathers, ſaying unto</hi> Abraham, <hi>in thy ſeed ſhall all the kindreds of the Earth be bleſſed, unto you firſt, God having raiſed up his Son Jeſus, ſent
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:106057:4"/> him to bleſs you, in turning away every one of you from his iniquities,</hi> Acts 3. 25, 26. Again, <hi>Bleſſed are they whoſe iniquities are forgiven, and whoſe ſins are covered,</hi> Rom. 4. 7. And again, <hi>Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual bleſſings, in heavenly places in Chriſt, in whom we have Redemption through his blood, the forgiveneſs of ſins according to the Riches of his Grace,</hi> Eph. 1. 3, 7. by which it is evident that Chriſts ſpiritual bleſſing beſtowed on thoſe Infants brought to him, was the pardon of their ſins, and that Chriſt had power on earth to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>give ſins, <hi>Matth.</hi> 9. 6. As for Temporal bleſſings, Chriſt himſelf was miniſtred unto of their ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance that followed him, <hi>Luke</hi> 8. 2, 3. and refuſed to divide temporal inheritances, <hi>Luke</hi> 12. 13. 14.</p>
            <p>Secondly, The neceſſity the Children brought to Chriſt, had of this Bleſſing; Becauſe it is writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, through the offence (or fall) of one, many are dead; By the offence of one, Judgment came upon all men to condemnation, by one m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ns diſobedience, many were made ſinners, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 15, 18, 19. In <hi>Adam</hi> all dyed, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 22. So that by nature we were the children of wrath, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2, 1. 3. As it is written, <hi>Who can bring a clean thing out of an unclean, no not one,</hi> Job 14. 4 So that a Wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man was unclean many dayes becauſe of Child<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bearing, <hi>Levit.</hi> 12. both Jews and Gentiles are all under ſin, as it is written, <hi>There is none Righte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous, no not one,</hi> Rom. 3. 9, 10, 11, 12. <hi>David</hi> like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe complaineth, <hi>Behold I was ſhapen in iniquity, and in ſin did my mother conceive me,</hi> Pſal. 51. 8. Likewiſe the Prophet calleth <hi>Iſrael,</hi> tranſgreſſors from the womb, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 48. 8. Yea the wicked are eſtranged from the womb, they go aſtray aſſoon as they be born, ſpeaking lyes, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 58. 3. there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:106057:4"/> I may by the teſtimony of theſe Scriptures, conclude, by like equality, that if <hi>Levi</hi> in the loyns of <hi>Abraham,</hi> before he was born, payed Tythes when <hi>Abraham</hi> did, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 9, 10. we likewiſe in the loyns of our Father <hi>Adam,</hi> before we were born, broke Gods Law when <hi>Adam</hi> did, <hi>Rom.</hi> 5. 12. for <hi>Adam</hi> was the root of all mankind, <hi>Acts</hi> 17. 26.</p>
            <p>Therefore it doth appear, That the children brought to Chriſt were very ſinful, and Chriſts bleſſing beſtowed on them, was the pardon or re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin; and Baptiſm of water is the ſign of remiſſion or forgiveneſs of ſins, what man of any underſtanding, can deny that thoſe that Chriſt hath bleſſed with a ſpiritual bleſſing, hath not right to Baptiſm of water.</p>
            <p>Moreover it was foretold by the Prophet, that Chriſt ſhould ſet up his ſtandard to the people, and lift up his hand to the Gentiles, and they ſhall bring thy ſons in their <note n="*" place="margin">or boſom.</note> arms and thy daughters ſhould be carried upon their ſhoulders, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 49. 22. which Scripture was fulfilled by thoſe that came and brought their little ones with them, which the Lord Jeſus him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf ſaith were of his Kingdome, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 14. and being before proved they were ſo ſinful, they had great neceſſity of Chriſts bleſſing, in having their ſin pardoned, for the children of Believers are the Lords, (<hi>Ezek.</hi> 16. 20, 21.) as well as their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents; therefore are called a choſen Generation, and a holy Nation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2. 9. If then they are equal with their Parents in acceptance of the par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don of their ſin, what reaſon can be given that they ſhall not be equal in having the ſign of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſin even Baptiſme of water, ſeeing the Scripture ſaith, that the promiſe is to you and your children, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38, 39.</p>
            <pb n="8" facs="tcp:106057:5"/>
            <p>Thirdly, The benefit thoſe children held in Arms, brought to Chriſt, and all the Children of Believers have of Chriſts Spiritual bleſſing, we have before proved, the bleſſing, even the pardon of ſins which Chriſt beſtowed on little Children: Now it followeth to be manifeſted, the happy e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate the children of Believers have, by Gods gift unto them by the benefit of Chriſts bleſſing.</p>
            <p>Firſt, They are accepted with their Parents in holy Covenant with the Lord, as it is written, <hi>Ye ſtand this day all of you before the Lord your God, your Captains of your Tribes, your Elders and your Officers</hi> (with) <hi>all the men of Iſrael, your little ones, your wives, and thy ſtranger that is in thy Camp, from the hewer of thy wood, unto the drawer of thy water, that thou ſhouldeſt enter into Covenant with the Lord thy God, and into his Oath which the Lord thy God maketh with thee this day, that he may establiſh thee to day, for a people to himſelf, and that he may be unto thee a God, as he hath ſaid unto thee, and as he hath ſworn unto thy Fathers, to</hi> Abraham, <hi>to</hi> Iſaac, <hi>and to</hi> Jacob; <hi>Nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with you only do I make this Covenant, and this Oath, but with him that ſtandeth here with us this day, before the Lord our God, and alſo with him that is not here with us this day,</hi> Deut. 29 10, 11, 12, 13, 14, 15. thus we ſee the little ones then preſent, and thoſe not then born, when their Fathers entred Covenant, the children entred Covenant with them, which was no other than the Covenant God made with <hi>Abraham</hi> here renewed: If chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren in infancy are with God accepted in holy Covenant, and all their ſins at that time were par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, <hi>Ezek. 16. 5, 6, 7, 8, 9. Rom.</hi> 3. 23, 24, 25. and Baptiſm a ſign of ſin pardoned, who can deny the children of the Covenant, who have their ſins par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doned, the Ordinance of Baptiſme any more than
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:106057:5"/> their Parents, ſeeing they are equal in the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38, 39.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Again the children of Believers are a part of the glory of Chriſts Kingdom, as it is written, And they ſhall hang upon him all the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of his Fathers houſe, the Off-ſpring and the Iſſue, all veſſels of ſmall quantity, from the veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of Cups, even to all the Veſſels of Flagons, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 22. 24. and as every Veſſel in the Temple of old, figured the bodies of the Saints, both great and ſmall, 2 <hi>Chron. 36. 18. Acts 9. 15. 1 Theſ.</hi> 4. 4. Therefore ſaith the Prophet, both young men and maidens, old men and children, let them praiſe the name of the Lord, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 148. 12, 13. So that little children in the Temple, cryed <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſanna</hi> to the ſon of <hi>David, Matth.</hi> 21. 15. the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nefit of Chriſts bleſſing upon the children of his Kingdom did here appear, and as it was foretold by the Prophet for the comfort of Believers, and their little ones, ſaying, <hi>I will pour my Spirit upon thy ſeed, and my bleſſing upon thine Off-ſpring, and they ſhall ſpring up</hi> (as) <hi>among the graſs, as Willows by the Water-courſes,</hi> Iſa. 44. 3, 4. which bleſſing is before proved to be the pardon of ſin, and Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm the ſign of remiſſion of ſin, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 39. who dare be ſo bold as to deny thoſe little ones who are a part of the glory of Chriſts Kingdom, as well as men of years, 2 <hi>Cor. 8. 23. Iſa.</hi> 22. 24. the bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fit of that Ordinance without rebellion againſt the Lord, and hatred to the Infants of Chriſts Kingdom?</p>
            <p>R. A's. Objections.</p>
            <p>Now I ſhall come to examine your Objection. You ſay it ſeemeth to you, that thoſe Children bleſt by Chriſt, were to receive it in future time, becauſe <hi>Matthew</hi> ſets down that thoſe little chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:106057:6"/> were brought that he ſhould put his hands on them, and pray (to wit) for a bleſſing on them; yet you confeſs Chriſts Prayers were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wayes heard, yet it doth not follow (ſay you) that he prayed for the bleſſing to be immediately be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtowed on thoſe Infants, nor that they did partake of it then, before they came to years of underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding (and this you ſay) you are the rather indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced to think, becauſe <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacobs</hi> bleſſings were not to be enjoyed till future times, <hi>Gen.</hi> 48. 49. and 27. 27.</p>
            <p>T. W's Anſwer.</p>
            <p>This you ſay, is but as you are induced to think, by paralelling the bleſſing of Chriſt with <hi>Iſaac</hi> and <hi>Jacobs,</hi> in reſpect of future time, to be enjoyed; your compariſon is not equal, and by it you do di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſh the Prerogative of Chriſt; did not, think you, all bleſſings of old point to Chriſt the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, for the ſpiritual fulfilling of them, and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pended upon no other for the accompliſhment? no nor in reſpect of time in future, for he is over all, God bleſſed for ever, Amen; for all the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes of God in him, are yea, and for him Amen; ſo that whom God doth bleſs, he or they are bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, as the Apoſtle ſaith, who hath bleſſed us, <hi>Eph.</hi> 1. 3. its the preſent time; even ſo ſaith <hi>Mark,</hi> and he took them up in his arms, put his hands upon them and bleſſed them, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 16. ſo that bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed are thoſe whoſe iniquities are forgiven, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 7. Thus it will undoubtedly follow to men that have the leaſt ſpark of true light, that thoſe whoſe ſins are pardoned, ought to have the ſign Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtred upon them, even Baptiſm of water.</p>
            <p>Moreover take notice, was not the bleſſing of the High Prieſt of old, <hi>Num.</hi> 6. 23, 24, 25, 26, 27. then enjoyed of the children of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> as figura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tively
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:106057:6"/> pointing to Chriſt our High Prieſt, now ſpiritually and more fu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ly by him fulfilled and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyed in his Church and Kingdom, who hath an unchangable Prieſthood, wherefore he is able alſo to ſave them to the uttermoſt that come unto God by him, ſeeing he ever liveth to make interceſſion for them, <hi>Heb.</hi> 7. 24, 25.</p>
            <p>Again, thoſe that were bleſt of old by the High Prieſt, had the name of the Lord put upon them, <hi>Numb.</hi> 6. 27. and Chriſt our High Prieſt came not to deſtroy the Law, but to fulfill it, <hi>Matth.</hi> 5. 17. So then, that as thoſe that the High Prieſt bleſt of old, had the name of the Lord put upon them, even ſo thoſe whom our High Prieſt doth bleſs with the pardon of ſins, ought to have his name put upon them, who is both Lord and Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 36. which is now done in the Ordinance of Baptiſm, in the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt; but Chriſt our High Prieſt did bleſs little Children held in arms with his ſpiritual bleſſing, the pardon of ſin, therefore ought ſuch little children to have his Name put upon them in the Ordinance of the Baptiſm of water.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. A.</hi> Your next Argument is, If thoſe Infants bleſt by Chriſt were not Baptiſed, then it is not likely that they had by that bleſſing, any right to Baptiſm of water, becauſe, if they had right to it, Chriſt would have had them been Baptiſed.</p>
            <p>But thoſe Infants bleſt by Chriſt were not Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed, for Chriſt himſelf Baptiſed not at all, <hi>John</hi> 4. 2. and what was done to the Infants, was done by Chriſt himſelf, as appears by the Text it ſelf, <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 13.</p>
            <p>Therefore thoſe Infant's bleſt by Chriſt, had not right to Baptiſm of water.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:106057:7"/>
            <p>T. W. his Anſwer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>The ſubſtance of your Argument is, That is the children had right by Chriſts bleſſing to Baptiſm of water, then would Chriſt have had them been Baptiſed.</p>
            <p>If this be a ground of Faith, it ſhould have bin proved by the Word of Faith, or a true gathered conſequence from the ſame, but that this your Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument to prove the Children whom Chriſt bleſt had no right to Baptiſm of Water, is neither from the word of truth, nor true gathered conſequence from the ſame, as ſhall plainly appear.</p>
            <p>We read many Diſciples believed in Chriſt, out of which he choſe Apoſtles, whom be bleſſed, as it is written, <hi>And he lift up his hands and bleſſed them,</hi> Luke 24. 50. yet we find not whether they were Baptiſed, any more then thoſe Infants which Chriſt likewiſe bleſſed, ſhall we conclude they were not Baptiſed, becauſe it is not written that Chriſt commanded them to be Baptiſed? conſider and lean not to your own underſtanding, <hi>Prov.</hi> 3. 5.</p>
            <p>Again, whereas you ſay Chriſt himſelf Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed not at all. I anſwer, It belonged not to his Office, for <hi>John</hi> taught, Chriſts Office was to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe with the Holy Ghoſt, and with Fire, <hi>Matth.</hi> 3. 11. and you are very bold to ſay, that what was done to thoſe Infants, was done by Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, you by like grounds might ſay, that what was done to the Diſciples whom Chriſt bleſſed, <hi>Luke</hi> 24. 50. was done by Chriſt himſelf, and we read he Baptiſed not at all, ſo by your grounds, neither the Infants, nor the Apoſtles whom Chriſt bleſſed, were at all Baptiſed with water, which is dangerous to believe.</p>
            <p>Again, you ſay it doth not appear that all the Infants of Believers are bleſſed with Chriſts Spiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:106057:7"/> bleſſing, as thoſe Infants were in <hi>Mark</hi> 10. 13.</p>
            <p>T. W. his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>It is evident, that as Chriſt ſaith by little Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren whom he bleſſed with his ſpiritual bleſſing, of ſuch is the Kingdome of God, which is his Church, <hi>Col. 1. 13. 1 Theſ. 2. 12. Rev.</hi> 1. 9. and as the Church or Congregation of old conſiſted of men, women, and children, <hi>Ezra</hi> 10. 1. called al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo a holy Nation, <hi>Exod.</hi> 19. 6. Even ſo the Church under the Goſpel conſiſteth of men, women, and children, <hi>Luke 18. 16. 2 John 1. 4. Epheſ. 6. 4. Gal. 4. 28. 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 14. being a choſen Generation, a Royal Prieſthood, a holy Nation which cannot be without children, then as the Apoſtle applyeth the ſpiritual bleſſing of Chriſt to the whole Church excluding none, but ſaith <hi>Epheſ. 1. 3. Bleſſed be the God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who hath bleſſed us with all ſpiritual bleſſings;</hi> ſo that as the whole is viſibly bleſſed, and the children with their Parents are in the ſame, muſt needs therefore be bleſſed with them, thus I hope your Arguments are fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>Moreover though this point be ſufficiently pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, yet if poſſible you may be convinced, and ſee how you are deceived concerning the eſtate of the Infants of Believers.</p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Jeremiah</hi> 11. 16. the Lord called thy name (ſpeaking to his beloved, <hi>ver.</hi> 15.) a green Olive Tree, fair, and of goodly fruit, and their children are likened to Olive Plants, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 128. and becauſe they rejected Chriſt and his ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants, which were ſent with the Goſpel to them, they were broken off, becauſe of unbelief, <hi>Rom 11. Acts</hi> 13. 45, 46. and their children in infancy were broken off with them, though ignorant of their
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106057:8"/> Fathers Rebellion; therefore ſeeing the condition both of Fathers and children was all one, he ſaid unto them, Repent and be Baptiſed every one of you, in the Name of the Lord Jeſus, for the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſion of ſins, for the Promiſe is to you and your children; and now can any one believe but that the children, upon the Fathers Repentance, are as capable to believe in the belief of their Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, and ſo grafted in the true Olive Tree, Chriſt, with their Parents again, as they were of unbelief and rebellion in their Parents unbelief and rebellion? So then, upon the Parents Repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance, who can hinder the children of thoſe Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penting Parents from the Ordinance of Baptiſm of Water with their Parents, ſeeing they were cut off with them, and the Ordinance a ſign of the pardon of ſins.</p>
            <p>From whence may juſtly be concluded, that if the Infants of Rebellions Jews were cut or broken off in their infancy with their Parents, though ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norant of their Parents Rebellion.</p>
            <p>Even ſo both Jews and Gentiles comming to the obedience of the Faith of Chriſt, though their Children in infancy be ignorant of their Fathers obedience, muſt of neceſſity be excepted with them.</p>
            <p>And that we may the better underſtand the ſcope of the Apoſtles Doctrine, the Doctrine be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, Repent and be Baptiſed every one of you, for the remiſſion of ſins, the reaſon is, For the promiſe is to you and your children. Take no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tice and obſerve, whether the Precept of Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is not to reach ſo far as the Reaſons thereunto doth extend, as may be ſeen <hi>Deut. 7. 1. 4. Ezra 9. 2, 11, 12. 2 Chron.</hi> 21. 6. Now the Doctrine is, Repent and be Baptiſed; and the Reaſon is, For
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:106057:8"/> the Promiſe is to you and your children, ſo that mention being made of children in the Reaſon, therefore the Precept of Baptiſing here ſpoken, implieth the children alſo.</p>
            <p>Otherwiſe how can you prove at the firſt cele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bration of the Lords Supper, that women ſhould be partakers thereof, ſeeing neither there, nor any other where in Chriſts Teſtament, any mention of any Woman by name were preſent, or partook thereof; as concerning children you require us to ſhew a child by name that was Baptiſed; yet ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Reaſons that are annexed to the Precept do neceſſarily imply women as well as men, and there is no Prohibition to the contrary, and cannot be denyed them without great ſin, <hi>Matth. 26. 20, 26, 27, 28. Luke 22. 14, 19, 20. 1 Cor.</hi> 11. 23, 24, 25. Now then conſider, how in this Ordinance you will grant that women may partake there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, though no name of any Woman that did, is expreſſed, but that children may partake of the Ordinance of Baptiſm, becauſe there is no menti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of any child by name that did, though there is as good reaſon, and true gathered conſequence from the Scripture for the one as the other, in this all men may ſee you are partial, and wilfully blind.</p>
            <p>Again, the people of your Judgment ſeem more unreaſonable to me in this point, of denying In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fants of Believers Baptiſm, than the <hi>Sadduces</hi> which denyed the reſurrection of the body, whom Chriſt put to ſilence by conſequence from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, without the litteral words of Scripture: to ſay the body ſhall riſe again, as may be ſeen in <hi>Exod.</hi> 3. 6. compared with <hi>Matth.</hi> 22. 31, 32. and as the Text ſaith, they were put to ſilence, ver. 34. and the multitude were aſtoniſhed at his Doctrine.
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:106057:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="15" facs="tcp:106057:9"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:106057:10"/> ver. 33. Likewiſe there is the Doctrine of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6. 2. and any of underſtanding in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture know, that Doctrine is the ſenſe and intend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of Scripture, for the natural man reads only the Letter, as the Eunuch did when he read in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. 7. as it is written in <hi>Acts</hi> 8. 32. the place of Scripture which he read was this, <hi>He was led as a ſheep to the ſlaughter, and like a lamb dumb before his ſhearers, ſo opened he not his mouth:</hi> ſee ver. 33. and ver. 34. the Eunuch anſwered <hi>Philip,</hi> and ſaid, <hi>I pray thee of whom ſpeaketh the Prophet this, of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf or ſome other man,</hi> ver. 35. <hi>Then</hi> Philip <hi>opened his mouth, and began at the ſame Scripture, and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched unto him Jeſus;</hi> but had the Eunuch bin an Anabaptiſt in Judgment, he would not have be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved <hi>Philip,</hi> to Preach Jeſus from that 53, of <hi>Iſa.</hi> when the word Jeſus was not expreſſed by name, and though the Apoſtles did Baptiſe Believers and their houſholds, 1 <hi>Cor. 1. 16. Acts</hi> 16. yet you will not believe that he Baptiſed Children, though the word Houſhold, are the children, as ſhall in this Treatiſe moſt plainly appear, as in <hi>Iſa.</hi> 53. Jeſus was intended in the Text by the word Lamb, ſo that I hope, not only you (unleſs you ſhut your eyes) but others ſhall ſee by the Holy Ghoſts own expoſition, according to his own counſel, compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 13. knowing this firſt, that no Propheſy of the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture is of any private interpretation, 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. 20. but a publick interpretation is for one Scripture to unfold another, as when <hi>Ezra</hi> and the people re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turned out of Captivity, <hi>Neh.</hi> 8. 8. he read in the Book of the Law diſtinctly, and gave the ſenſe, and cauſed them to underſtand the reading, ſo that I hope, that if the Scripture do expound the hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhold to be children, ſeeing the Apoſtle did Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:106057:10"/> houſholds, you will believe he did Baptiſe Children, and ſo repent of your error in denying the ſame, and leave off deluding the people through your former ignorance.</p>
            <p>Next then to obſerve, that little children which do partake of Chriſts ſpiritual bleſſing, have not only right to Baptiſm of Water, but were alſo Baptiſed by the hands of the Apoſtles.</p>
            <p>Though ſome will think this Argument can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be proved, becauſe the natural man receiveth not the things of the Spirit of God, for they are fooliſhneſs unto him, neither can he know them, becauſe they are ſpiritually diſcerned, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 14. obſerve the Lords Covenant of old made with the faithful, and their ſeed in infancy, and the words of the Covenant was, <hi>To be a God unto thee, and to thy ſeed after thee,</hi> Gen. 17. 7. So that <hi>Abraham</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lieved God, and it was accounted to him for righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſneſs, and they that are of Faith, the ſame are the children of <hi>Abraham,</hi> Gal. 3. 6, 7. and the children of the Promiſe are counted for the ſe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>d<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but <hi>Iſaac</hi> was a child of Promiſe in Infancy, <hi>Gal.</hi> 4. 28. even an heir of life, 1 <hi>John</hi> 2. 25. and had the ſeal of Faith adminiſtred upon him, and I hope none will be ſo bold to ſay, it was a lying ſign or ſeal to ſeal to him that he had not, but of this we ſhall have occaſion to handle anon; but now to prove that a mans children are his houſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold.</p>
            <p>We read, <hi>Gen.</hi> 45. 11. and 46. 5, 6, 7, 8. that <hi>Joſeph</hi> is ſaid to nouriſh his Father and his Bre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thren, and all his Fathers houſhold, according to their Families, which is expounded, I will nouriſh you and your little ones, <hi>Gen.</hi> 50. 21. and it is l<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe ſaid, David <hi>dwelt with</hi> Achiſh <hi>at</hi> Gath, <hi>he and his men, every man with his h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>uſhold,</hi> 1 Sam. 27. 3.
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:106057:11"/> which is expounded to be their Sons and daugh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 30. 6. If there were no more evidence than theſe two Witneſſes, it might ſuffice reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, but all men have not faith, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore do they muddy the water of Gods truth with their feet, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 34. 18, 19. but there is a pure Ri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver of water of life, clear as Chryſtal, proceeding out of the Throne of God, and of the Lamb, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 1. to confirm the ſpirits of the faithful from theſe mens abuſe of Scripture.</p>
            <p>We read in <hi>Deut.</hi> 25. If two brethren dwell to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, and one of them dye and have no child, the Wife of the dead ſhall not marry without unto a ſtranger, her Husbands Brother ſhall go in unto her, and take her to him to Wife, and perform the duty of an Husbands brother unto her, and it ſhall be that the firſt born which ſhe beareth, ſhall ſucceed in the name of his brother which is dead, that his name be not put out of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> ver. 5, 6. and in the ſeventh verſe, If the man like not to take his Brothers wife, ſee in ver. 9. then ſhall his Bro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers wife come unto him in the preſence of the Elders, and looſe his ſhoe from off his foot, and ſpit in his face, and ſhall anſwer and ſay, So ſhall it be done unto that man that will not build up his Brothers houſe; how plainly doth it appear in this place, that a mans children are his houſe; A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, the Elders prayed the Lord to make <hi>Ruth</hi> like <hi>Leah</hi> and <hi>Rachel,</hi> which built the houſe of <hi>Iſrael, Ruth</hi> 4. 11. which were their children; and again, the Widdow of <hi>Zareptha's</hi> ſon was called her houſe, read 1 <hi>Kings</hi> 17. 12, 13, 14, 15. verſes. Again, a Biſhop or Paſtor muſt be one that ruleth well his own houſe, having his children in ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 3. 4, 5. and again <hi>Jacob</hi> went down into <hi>Egypt,</hi> every man and his houſhould, which
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:106057:11"/> were their children, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. and where perſons had no children, ſee what God ſaith (promiſing to give children) he maketh the barren woman to keep houſe (or dwell in a houſe) and to be a joy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful mother of children, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 113. 9. which is far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther confirmed in that ſenſe; and it came to paſs becauſe the Midwives feared God, he made them houſes, <hi>Exod.</hi> 1. 21. compared with 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 2. 35. and the cauſe why <hi>Sarah</hi> gave her Maid <hi>Hagar</hi> to <hi>Abraham,</hi> that ſhe might be builded up<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by her <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. 2. (or obtain children); thus I hope no Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience can doubt or ſcruple, or think the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trary, but that the children is the mans houſe or houſhould, and the Apoſtle Baptiſing Believers and their houſhould or houſe, did with his own hands Baptiſe Believers and their children; thus your ſtumbling block is taken out of the way, if God be pleaſed to open your eyes to ſee it.</p>
            <p>R. A's. Objection.</p>
            <p>Becauſe you cannot ſee the children of the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful bring forth the fruits of faith, you preſume to ſay they have not faith.</p>
            <p>T. W. his Anſwer.</p>
            <p>Might not one by your ground ſay, that a child of 8 dayes old cannot have all the faculties of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture in him as a man (though the Holy Ghoſt ſaith, a child is born a man, <hi>John</hi> 16. 21.) in the bud or beginning, as hearing, ſeeing, ſmelling, ſpeak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and the like; yet becauſe the child cannot hear underſtandingly, and ſee perceivingly, and ſmell diſtinguiſhingly, and ſpeak plainly as a man of years, ſhall one conclude he hath not the facul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties in him in the bud; but little children Chriſt ſaith are of the Kingdom of God. which is the houſhould of Faith, <hi>Gal.</hi> 6. 10. and can any be of the houſhould of Faith, and want Faith; therefore
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:106057:12"/> as the world knoweth not Chriſt, nor the ſubjects of his Kingdom, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 1. they muſt needs be but as the world, to ſay thoſe have not faith which are of Chriſts Kingdom, and with <hi>Nicodemus</hi> ſay, how can th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ſe things be? <hi>John</hi> 3.</p>
            <p>Again, we read <hi>Iſaac</hi> was Circumciſed at eight dayes old; the Apoſtle calleth Circumciſion a ſeal of the righteouſneſs of Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. and the children of Believers are as capable of Faith at eight dayes old now in Goſpel times, as before the Law; the Prophet ſpeaking of Goſpel times, ſaith, their children ſhall be as afore-time, <hi>Jer.</hi> 30. 20. ſo that as Circumciſion was a ſign of Faith and holineſs, <hi>Rom.</hi> 4. 11. and 2. 29. <hi>Col. 2. 11. Deut.</hi> 10. 16. even ſo is Baptiſm now, <hi>Acts 8. 37, 38. Rom</hi> 6. 3, 4.</p>
            <p>The Covenant of the Goſpel with <hi>Abraham,</hi> is the ſame now in ſubſtance, <hi>Gal. 3. 8. Gen. 17. 4, 5. Rom.</hi> 4. 13, 16, 17. the Covenan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> with <hi>Abraham</hi> was, that the Lord would be a God to him, and his ſeed after him, <hi>Gen.</hi> 17. 7. as, <hi>Bleſſed is that Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion whoſe God is the Lord,</hi> Pſal. 33. 12. this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſedneſs commeth on none by the Law, <hi>Rom. 4. 15. Gal.</hi> 3. 10, 11, 12. and that the Lord will be a God to us, and we his people, is the Goſpel in the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, <hi>Heb. 8. 10. Rev. 21. 3. 2 Cor.</hi> 6. 16. and Chriſt was a Miniſter of the Circumciſion, to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm the Promiſe made to the Fathers, which they believed (Chriſt was to come) &amp; we believe he is come) <hi>Luke 1. 69, 72, 73. Acts</hi> 13. 32, 33. being one faith of Gods elect, <hi>Gal. 3. 9. Heb.</hi> 11. and we believing Gentiles, fellow Heirs, and of the ſame body with the Believing Jews, therefore I may juſtly conclude, That which was once command<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of God, and never repealed, ought ſtill to be done.</p>
            <pb n="21" facs="tcp:106057:12"/>
            <p>But God commanded the ſign or ſeal of faith and holineſs to the faithful and their ſeed, and never yet repealed, therefore ought ſtill to be done.</p>
            <p>But if any object that Circumciſion was a ſeal of the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> the Apoſtle ought to be be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liev'd before them, who ſaith, <hi>It was a Seal of faith;</hi> and for farther manifeſting of their folly that ſay, It was a ſeal of <hi>Canaan;</hi> for <hi>Abraham,</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Jacob</hi> were Circumciſed, and they never paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed it according to the promiſe, nor their Genera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, till they came out of <hi>Egypt,</hi> but dwelt as ſtrangers in it, <hi>Heb.</hi> 11. 9.</p>
            <p>Again, as uncleanneſs is oppoſite to holineſs, when the fruit of the Land of <hi>Canaan</hi> was forbid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> three years, it ſhould be as uncircumciſed unto them, and not to be eaten, and in the fourth year all the fruit thereof ſhall be holy, <hi>Lev.</hi> 19. 23, 24. thus we ſee that Circumci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion is a ſign of holineſs.</p>
            <p>Again, we read that God promiſeth to Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſe the hearts of his people to love him, <hi>Deut.</hi> 30. 6. which is no leſs than a clean heart, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 51. 10. which is no leſs than putting off the body of ſins by the Circumciſion of Chriſt, <hi>Col.</hi> 2. 11. and when men do not hear and obey the Lord, they are ſaid to have uncircumciſed ears, <hi>Jer.</hi> 6. 10. Thus we may ſee plainly, that Circumciſion was a ſign of holineſs, and not of <hi>Canaan;</hi> and if it had been a ſign of the Promiſe of the Land, what need had they to Circumciſe any more when they poſſeſſed the land; thus let all men beware of theſe blind guides, that heed not what they ſay to maintain their errors.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>R. A.</hi> Again you ſay, If by the everlaſting Covenant be meant all the children of Believers
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:106057:13"/> are in the covenant of grace, and ſo to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed (you ſay) it is falſe, for whoſoever is truly in the Covenant of Grace, can never fall finally a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way from it, <hi>Eſay</hi> 54. 10. <hi>Jer.</hi> 31. 3. and 9. But (ſay you) the Children of Believers may and do prove wicked and be reprobates, witneſſe <hi>Iſhmael, Eſau, &amp;c.</hi> therefore it appears, all the children of Believers are not in the Covenant of Grace; and ſo none to be baptized till ſome declarative ſign, to know which are in the Covenant of Grace, which will not be made manifeſt till they are grown up and able to make profeſſion of Faith, and then we have that we contend for.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> It is well known, that we believe Electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and I am glad you do not deny Election: but ſecret things belong to God, and revealed things to us and to our children, <hi>Deut.</hi> 29. 29. but when the Lord made his Covenant with <hi>Abraham</hi> and his Seed, he was commanded to adminiſter the Seal of Faith to his children in infancy, whether they would ſtand or fall, he had no Rule to queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: nor you if you were guided by that Spirit that guided him, and if he and the children of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> ſhould have been of your belief, when <hi>Iſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mael</hi> became a mocker, and <hi>Eſau</hi> a prophane per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, having both the outward Seal of Faith, they would have circumciſed no more, leſt they had not Faith; becauſe ſome do fall away, had they done well think you? but having no ſuch Rule from God, they would not follow their own ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits as you do, like the falſe Prophets in <hi>Iſrael</hi> that had ſeen nothing, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. 3. But the faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full had learned to obey, which is better than ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, and to hearken than the fat of Rambs, 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15. 22. and that which is highly eſteemed among men is abominable in the ſight of God,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:106057:13"/> 
               <hi>Luk.</hi> 16. 15. And how highly eſteem'd is this error among the people of your Judgment, to deny the outward Seal of the Covenant of God to the Seed of the Faithfull without warrant from his Word.</p>
            <p>Moreover, If we ſhould not baptize our Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, becauſe ſome may fall away and become as <hi>Iſhmael</hi> and <hi>Eſau,</hi> by like grounds you ſhould not baptize elder people, becauſe after they fall away, as <hi>Symon Magus, Demas,</hi> &amp; the like &amp; ſo to follow your fantaſy rather than Faith, and neglect Gods Ordinance, becauſe we cannot enter into Gods Seat to know the heart: Let all beware of this, as <hi>Solomon</hi> ſaith, <hi>There is a way that ſeemeth right unto man, but the end thereof are the wayes of death,</hi> Pro. 16. 25.</p>
            <p>Again, If one by carnall reaſon ſhould follow your ſteps, to ſay that the Children of Believers have not Faith, becauſe the fruits of Faith doth not yet appear, they might reaſon againſt you, and ſay, that there is none of your Judgment do yet believe, becauſe it is ſaid, <hi>Theſe ſigns ſhall follow them that believe; they ſhall caſt out devils and ſpeak with new Tongues. They ſhall take up Serpents, and if they drink any deadly poyſon, it ſhall not hurt them, they ſhall lay their hands on the ſick, and they ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover,</hi> Mark 16. 17, 18. Now conſider, becauſe that theſe ſigns do not now attend believers, ſince extraordinary Officers ceaſed, do none believe therefore? So though the Apoſtle ſaith, That Circumciſion was the Seal of Faith, and it was no lying ſign, ſhall any ſay, that Children have or had not Faith, becauſe we cannot ſee the ſigns of Faith. Remember what the Wiſeman ſaith. Be not over juſt.</p>
            <p>Now to conclude this point, conſider what God ſaith of the Children of his People, <hi>Even the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:106057:14"/> houſe of</hi> Jacob, <hi>and all the remnant of the houſe of</hi> Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael, <hi>(which) are born (by me) from the belly, (which are) carried from the womb. Even to old age,</hi> &amp;c. Iſa. 46. 3, 4. And again, <hi>The Lord hath called me from the womb, from the bowels of my mother hath he made mention of my name,</hi> Eſa. 49. 1. And in verſe 5. <hi>And now, ſaith the Lord, that formed me from the womb to be his ſervant:</hi> And again, <hi>I formed thee in the belly, I knew thee, and before thou cameſt forth of the womb, I ſanctified thee,</hi> Jer. 1. 5. And again, <hi>The babe leaped in the womb for joy,</hi> Luke 1. 44. Thus the children of Gods people are born unto the Lord, as it written; <hi>Thou haſt taken my ſons and my daughters, whom thou haſt born unto me:</hi> And again, <hi>Thou haſt ſtain my children,</hi> Ezek. 16. 20, 21. Which children are a holy ſeed, <hi>Ezra</hi> 9. 2. <hi>Iſa.</hi> 6. 13. <hi>Jer.</hi> 2. 3. 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 7. 14. <hi>Mal.</hi> 2. 15. Which cannot be without Gods Spirit which ſanctifieth all that have it, 1 <hi>Theſ. 4. 7, 8. 2 Cor.</hi> 1. 21, 22. Which Spirit is the Spirit of Faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13. Therefore having the Spirit of Faith they are Chriſts, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 9. (Or elſe none of his) now how clear a matter is this, that Infants are the Lords and Chriſt, and ſo have his ſpirit? We ſhall con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude with the holy Spirit, that the children of the faithfull have right to Baptiſm, as it is written, can any man forbid water, that theſe ſhould not be baptized which have received the holy Ghoſt as well as we, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 47. Now let none reaſon with <hi>Nicodemus, How can theſe things be?</hi> John 3. 9. But in ſobriey ſay with <hi>Solomon, As thou knoweſt not (what is the way of the Spirit, nor how the bones (do grow) in the womb of her that is with child: even ſo thou knoweſt not the works of God who maketh all,</hi> Eccle. 11. 5.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Object.</hi> If any further object and ſay, that <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham</hi>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:106057:14"/> was commanded to command his chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren and his houſhold, ſuppoſing that a mans ſervants are his houſhold.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw. Abraham</hi> was a Prophet, and at that time the Church of God was under his govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, ſo that as he was a Prophet and Over-ſee<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> the Lord knew he would feed the Church of God, as he was a Father, he would teach his Children the nurture and admonition of the Lord, <hi>Eph.</hi> 6. So that he and all true Paſtors that was fit accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the rule, muſt both rule his own children, <hi>having them in ſubjection with all gravity: for if a man know not how to rule his own houſe, how ſhall he take car<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> of the Church of God?</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 4. 5.</p>
            <p>And that a mans ſervants are not called his houſe or houſhold, but are diſtinguiſhed by the holy Ghoſt called houſhold-ſervants, <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 7. As a mans goods are called houſhold-ſtuffe, <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hemiah</hi> 15. 8. Thus I ſuppoſe the Objection is fully anſwered.</p>
            <p>And now my friend I ſhall endeavour accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to that ſmall underſtanding I have, to open the ſignification of the word Baptiſm, by context of Scripture, (which you build your Faith ſo much upon) and to ſhew you how you deceive your ſelves, in binding, limiting and confining the word to ſignifie only to dip, plung, overwhelm without warrant of the learned in the Tongues or ſenſe of holy Scripture.</p>
            <p>I muſt acknowledge my ſelfe the unfitteſt of many, to intermeddle with a work of this nature, by reaſon of my want of skill in the Tongues, as you likewiſe acknowledg the ſame, yet you bring many Authors to prove the word Baptize to ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifie to dip: yet you confeſs, they ſay it alſo ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nifieth to waſh or ſprinckle, ſo that by your own
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:106057:15"/> grant, the teſtimony of the Learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed proveth no more for <note n="*" place="margin">It is error to confine it as you do.</note> you then againſt you: and foraſmuch as the Learned themſelves, are at their wits end concerning the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nfication of ſome words in holy Scripture, as in <hi>Job</hi> 2. 9. Some ſay where it is tranſlated Curſe, other ſay Bleſs alſo, the word <hi>Euriclydon, Act.</hi> 27. 14. One ſaith it ſignifieth a North-Eaſt wind, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother a ſoultery hot wind, but foraſmuch as many words in Scripture are left by the learned in the original Term, though in Engliſh Letters, as Baptize, <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> and many the like. It be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoveth you &amp; I, being Engliſhmen, not wholy to rely upon the learned in Tongues, ſeeing the Jewiſh Rabins skilfull in Tongues, did not all of them underſtand the true ſenſe or meaning of the Scripture, nor yet to ſlight or lightly eſteem of the worthy endeavours of the learned in tranſlating the Scriptures, who have dealt ſo honeſtly, where they durſt not confine the word to one ſenſe or tearm, they left it to be underſtood by the people of God as the Spirit of the Lord ſhould direct them.</p>
            <p>The word <hi>Meſſiah,</hi> being alledged againſt a Jew to prove the death of Chriſt, how the Angel pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſied <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſhould be ſlain, <hi>Dan.</hi> 9. 26. I (ſaith the Jew) but <hi>Meſſiah</hi> ſignfieth any one that is anoynted Governor; ſo that when words in Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture have large or divers ſignifications, we ought carefully and wiſely to conſider the divers uſe and meaning of them, to agree in a harmony of holy Scripture. Likewiſe <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ell an Athieſt, that God made the Heavens and the Earth, <hi>Gen.</hi> 1. 1. He may anſwer as the Learned in the Tongues ſay, <hi>Aelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>him</hi> ſometimes is uſed to ſignifie Angels, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 8.
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:106057:15"/> 5. with <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. 7. ſometimes to ſignifie magi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrates, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 82. 1, 6. therefore he believes not a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch God properly as we profeſs: not having Gods Spirit to underſtand the ſenſe and true in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendment thereof.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe the originall word for worſhip as the Learned do expreſs the ſame <hi>Latria</hi> and <hi>Latréuo</hi> ſometimes largely uſed, and ſometimes more ſtrictly; ſo that word worſhip generally compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth the performance of all duties required in the firſt Table of Gods Law, <hi>Deut.</hi> 5. 6. 15. more ſtrictly and properly to worſhip is to bow down and ſupplicate to God, <hi>Mat.</hi> 2. 2.</p>
            <p>Again the originall word for Church, Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation or Aſſembly given in by the learned <hi>Kahal</hi> in Hebrew, and in Greek <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> which word is uſed for any Aſſembly, which without the help of Gods holy Spirit cannot be rightly divided, as the gathering together in a Market is <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> where Women as well as Men have equall privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge to ſpeak, yet the word <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> a gathering in a Church Aſſembly, where men and women have not equall priviledge alike to ſpeak, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 14. 34, 35. Likewiſe when but two or three are gathered together in Church worſhip, <hi>Mat.</hi> 18. 20. they bear the name <hi>Eccleſia,</hi> and when the Church conſiſteth of thouſands they are but <hi>Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſia, Acts 4. 4. Acts 7. 38. Exod.</hi> 19. 1, 3, 5. 6. So when it ſignifieth the leaſt, we are not to de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſe the day of ſmall things, <hi>Zech. 4. 10. Luk.</hi> 12. 32<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
            </p>
            <p>Likewiſe the word Saviour ſometimes ſignifieth Chriſt, ſometimes Chriſts Mini<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                  <desc>•••</desc>
               </gap>rs, <hi>Obadiah, ver. 21. 1 Tim.</hi> 4. 16. ſometimes civill Magiſtrates or Deliverers, <hi>Neh.</hi> 9. 27. which divers uſe is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proved by the Scriptures by which we ought to
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:106057:16"/> take the more notice of the word Baptize, which as is ſaid before, that the learned give in to ſignifie to dip, waſh, water, ſprinckle, ſo that my friend <hi>R. A.</hi> you are very bold upon you own head, and the men of your Judgment, to bind up the word Baptize to only dip without either the learneds aſſent or warrant of holy Scripture, therefore both you and all of your Judgment, conſider by what hath been ſaid, how many words in Scripture (a few before treated on) that cannot be confined without adding or diminiſhing from the mind of God (but to be underſtood by the directions of Gods Spirit) <hi>Rev. 22. 18. Deut. 4. 2. Pro.</hi> 30. 6. and learn the counſell of the Holy Ghoſt, of theſe things put them in remembrance, charging them before the Lord, that they ſtrive not about words to no profit, but to the ſubverting of the hearers: ſtudy to ſhew thy ſelf approved unto God a work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, that needeth not to be aſhamed, rightly divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding the word of truth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 14, 15.</p>
            <p>So then, foraſmuch, as the holy Scriptures hold forth three ſeveral Baptiſms by the one word Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, I ſhall endeavour by the help of the Lord to lay down ſome grounds according to the ſenſe of Scripture, how we may rightly divide the Word of Truth to underſtand the ſame, comparing ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall things with ſpirituall, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 2. 13. and not altogether rely on the learned in Tongues, though in due place and right uſe are not in the leaſt to be deſpiſed, but highly eſteemed, for we read the Book is given to one that is learned, <hi>Saying, Read this, I pray thee: and he ſaith, I cannot, for it is ſeal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed. And the Book is delivered to him that is not lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, ſaying, Read this I pray thee: and he ſaith, I am not learned,</hi> Eſay 29. 12. So that <hi>great is the myſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of godlineſſe,</hi> 1 Tim. 3. 16. So that when the
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:106057:16"/> holy Scriptures as ſo made uſe of, and interpret<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, that no one Scripture jar againſt another, but agree in one harmony; like as the Levites having Cymbals, and Pſalteries, and Harps, and with them an hundred and twenty Prieſts ſounding with Trumpets, they made but one ſound to praiſe the Lord, 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 5. 12. 13. ſo alſo the true Trumpets of Gods holy Truths make but one ſound, 1 <hi>Theſ. 1. 8. Rom</hi> 15. 6. to praiſe the Lord, which none can learn but the redeemed from the earth, <hi>Rev.</hi> 14. they can tune both old and new Teſtament, to agree in one harmony of melody and ſoul comfort, <hi>Pſal. 81. 2. Rev. 14. 2. Rev.</hi> 15. 3. never a Scripture to jar one againſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother, by which learning our Lord and Maſter put to ſilence the learned Rabbins in the Mother Tongue, <hi>Mat.</hi> 22. 41, 42, to 46. with this learn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and wiſdom <hi>Stephen</hi> in diſputing, the Studi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ents were not able to reſiſt the wiſdom of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit by which he ſpake, <hi>Acts</hi> 6. 9, 10. But the un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>learned and unskilfull to reconcile the Scriptures to agree in one, as the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>They that are unlearned, and unſtable, wreſt as they do alſo the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Scriptures, unto their own deſtruction,</hi> 2 Peter 3. 16.</p>
            <p>Now then the whole Scriptures are called the Word of God, 1 <hi>Theſ. 2. 13. Luk.</hi> 8. 11. Yet as it hath many ſentences or words, as every word of God is pure, <hi>Prov.</hi> 30. 5. Yet it is called the word of God becauſe it agreeth in one harmony together, as when a controverſie fell out among the Church at <hi>Antioch,</hi> it was ended in reconciling both Old and New Teſtaments together, <hi>As it is written, to this agreeth the words of the Prophet,</hi> Acts 15. 15. And all the Apoſtles Doctrins agree with the Doctrins of the Prophets, <hi>Rev.</hi> 21. 12. 14 19.
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:106057:17"/> 
               <hi>Epheſ. 2. 20. Acts 26. 22. Acts 17. 11. Rom.</hi> 15. 4.</p>
            <p>Again, the Apoſtle ſaith, <hi>For there are three that bear record in Heaven, the Father, the Word, and the Holy Ghoſt: and theſe three are one. And there are three that bear witneſſe in earth, the Spirit, the Water, and the Blood: and theſe three agree in one,</hi> 1 Joh. 5. 7. 8.</p>
            <p>Even ſo there are three baptiſms, the baptiſm of the Spirit, <hi>Mat.</hi> 3. 11. the baptiſm of ſuffering, <hi>Mark 10. 38, 39. John</hi> 18. 11. and the baptiſm of Water, <hi>Acts</hi> 10 47. Yet the Apoſtle ſaith, there is but one baptiſm, <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 4. 5. So that there is but one word or tearm for theſe three baptiſms, and when they be rightly underſtood the ſignification of the word baptiſm will agree in one; ſo I ſhall begin with the firſt in order.</p>
            <p>The ſignification of the word baptiſm is open<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Spirit of God in the adminiſtration thereof in the ſpiritual baptiſm, to be a pouring forth, as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ntill the ſpirit be pour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on us from on high,</hi> Eſa. 32. 15. <hi>Ezek. 39. 29. Joel</hi> 2. 28. which was fulfilled in <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 17. 18. and 10. 45. So that by this one Spirit, the whole Church or body of Chriſt, conſiſting of men, wo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men &amp; children are baptiſed into one body, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 13. Being an holy nation, by the gift and ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctification of that holy Spirit, 1 <hi>Peter 2. 9. 1 Theſ. 4. 8. Rom 15. 16. Heb.</hi> 11. 2. And this baptiſm of the Spirit, is by the Spirit of God called ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, <hi>Ezek. 36. 25, 26. Heb. 9. 14. 1 Pet.</hi> 1. 2. in the manner of Rain, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77. 17.</p>
            <p>Secondly, There is alſo the Baptiſm of ſuffer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>Mark 10. 38, 39. Col.</hi> 1, 24. which the Saints or Members of Chriſts Body do partake of, <hi>Phil. 2. 17. 2 Cor.</hi> 1. 5, 6, 7. As for example, one ſuffers
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:106057:17"/> reproaches, <hi>Heb.</hi> 13. 13. others reproaches and loſſe of goods, <hi>Heb.</hi> 33. 34. others baniſhment, <hi>Eſa. 51. 14. Rev.</hi> 1. 9. others loſſe of life, <hi>Rev.</hi> 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>. 11. So every one according to the meaſure, the Lord is pleaſed they ſhall be exerciſed with, and theſe degrees of ſuffering ſome more, and ſome leſſe, is the word Baptiſm ſignified by, but ſhall a man ſay, that he that ſuffers reproaches, and not loſſe of goods, is not partaker of Baptiſm of ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering, or he, or they, that ſuffer loſſe of goods and baniſhment, and not loſſe of life, is he not parta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker of the baptiſm of ſuffering, becauſe he doth not partake in the largeſt ſenſe of the ſignification of the word baptiſm in ſuffering, conſider theſe things.</p>
            <p>And thirdly, There is alſo the Baptiſm of Water which being the ſame word as the two former in ſignification; and we ſee the baptiſm of the Spirit, is adminiſtred by pouring or ſprinkling and alſo in <hi>Iſa. So ſhall he ſprinkle many Nations, Iſa.</hi> 52. 15. ye we ſee every one hath not a like meaſure of the Spirit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 12. 3. but to every one is given grace according to the meaſure of the gift of Chriſt, he gave ſome Apoſtles, ſome Prophets, ſome Evangeliſts, ſome Paſtors, ſome Teachers, <hi>Eph.</hi> 4. And he that received leaſt received one tallent, and all the baptiſm of the Spirit: but ſhall a man ſay, becauſe he that received but one Tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, or the leaſt gift of the Spirit, that he is not partaker of the ſpiritual baptiſm, becauſe he hath not ten Tallents or the largeſt gift of the Spirit, he would be deceived in his underſtanding of the true meaning of the word, ſo as the word in the two former ſignifications is not nor cannot be tied up to one ſenſe according to the Scriptures, nor the teſtimony of the Learned, but ſignifieth more or
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:106057:18"/> leſſe water in the adminiſtration of the baptiſm of water, being performed in the order of God, therefore it is evill to confine the word in the ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nification to dipping or greateſt meaſure of the uſe of water: unleſſe the two other baptiſms of the Spirit and ſuffering could or ought to be confined to the greateſt meaſure of the Spirit and ſuffering; but the learned in the Tongues, as I conceive, durſt not confine the ſignification of the word Baptiſm to one ſenſe (as you preſumptuouſly do) but not only to dip, but to waſh, to water and ſprinkle, and did very faithfully to leave it in the tearm baptize, to be underſtood of all Gods peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, as his holy Spirit ſhould direct them by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>text of Scripture comparing ſpiritual things with ſpiritual, one Scripture unfolding another, by harmony of agreement; and this may be obſerv<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed for a general rule of Faith, that whatſoever Doctrin, Collection, or Obſervation for a truth, believed out of holy Scripture by any, If an ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurdity will fall upon it, then their ſuppoſed truth is but error, as for example, when ſome denyed the Reſurrection of the Body, the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> overthrew their collection by an abſurdity, that juſtly would fall upon it, in theſe words, <hi>If the dead riſe not, then is not Chriſt riſen, then is our preaching vain, and your faith is alſo vain,</hi> &amp; the like 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. So likewiſe if according to your under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding of the word Baptize, that it is only to be underſtood of the greateſt meaſure of waſhing by dipping, plunging, or overwhelming it, will then upon it, this abſurdity follow that he that hath not the greateſt meaſure of the baptiſm of the Spirit, as the Apoſtles, Prophets, and Evangeliſts, hath not the baptiſm of the Spirit, &amp; then the whol Church are not baptized by one Spirit into o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e Body (for
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:106057:18"/> every one had not a like meaſure, but had diverſities of gifts) then there is <note n="*" place="margin">Contrary to 1 Cor. 3. 1. 1 Pet. 2. 2.</note> no babes in Chriſt, but only thoſe that have the greateſt meaſure of knowledge, contrary to the Apoſtles doctrin, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 12. 4. 7, 8, 9, 10, 11, 12, 13. ſeeing that it hath the ſame word for the ſpiritual baptiſm as for the water, it muſt needs have the like ſenſe in ſignification, and if one may be tyed up to the largeſt ſenſe only, there is like reaſon for the other, and if not the one then not the other: thus my friend <hi>R. A.</hi> conſider, how you are deceived in your underſtanding of the true ſenſe of the word Baptize, and obſerve farther what ſignification the Spirit of God giveth of the word Baptize, <hi>Ananias</hi> ſaid unto <hi>Paul, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe, and be baptized, and waſh away thy ſins,</hi> Acts 22. 11. Which waſhing in ſign of cleanſing in the ordinance of baptiſm may be done with water in a Baſon, being called a waſhing, <hi>John</hi> 13. 5, 8. and a part being taken for the whole, as ſhall af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter more fully be proved that baptiſm of water was ſo performed on the perſon, a part taken for the whole, but ſince extraordinary gifts and officers are ceaſed, it will in the next place be needfull.</p>
            <p>Firſt, To know where Baptiſm ought to be performed.</p>
            <p>Secondly, Who are the true Adminiſtrators thereof.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, On what part of the Body, baptiſm of water, ought and is moſt likely by the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, it was adminiſtred upon.</p>
            <p>You bring many Scriptures, to ſhew that per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons that were baptized, went down into the wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:106057:19"/> and they came up out of the water, as <hi>Mat. 3. 16. Mark</hi> 1. 5. and they baptized in <hi>Enon,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there was much water, that thus the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſaith, is not denyed, but that the perſons were dipped theſe Scriptures ſpeak not, which if it were ſuppoſed that they were dipt; which you gather, yet that doth not prove it is not lawfull to waſh or ſprinckle in baptiſm, according to the foregoing grounds, from the ſignification of the word Baptize.</p>
            <p>But to come to my firſt particular, where bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Water ought to be performed, it is evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent where the word was preached, <hi>In thoſe dayes came</hi> John <hi>the Baptiſt, preaching in the Wilderneſſe of</hi> Judea. <hi>Then went out to him</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>and all</hi> Judea, <hi>and all the Region round about</hi> Jordan. <hi>And were baptized of him in</hi> Jordan, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Mat. 3. 1, 5, 6. So that it doth appear, where he taught, there he baptized, now where it ſaith, <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> and all <hi>Judea</hi> were baptized of him, here a part is taken for the whole, as doth appear in handling the next particular; and ſo we may underſtand in the uſe of water: likewiſe where the Eunuch was converted there he was baptized, for ſaith he, here is water, what doth hinder me to be bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed? <hi>Acts</hi> 10. 36. Likewiſe when <hi>Paul</hi> preached the word of the Lord, at midnight to the Jaylor, the Text ſaith, He took them the ſame hour of the night and waſhed their ſtripes, and was bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tized, he and all his ſtrait-way, ſo that there is no ground to think, that ſeeing that the Apoſtle was ſo grievouſly wounded that they ſhould go at midnight, to a Pond or River, up to the middle to baptize the Jaylor, and all his, but as I ſaid be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, where the word was preached and converſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:106057:19"/> wrought, that there the ordinance was performed by thoſe immediately which the Lord did ſend to begin that work.</p>
            <p>Moreover conſider, before the Tabernacle of old was reared up or built, Altars were builded at ſeveral times by ſeveral perſons, extraordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rily called thereunto of God, as <hi>Noah, Abraham, Jacob,</hi> and the like: but when the Tabernacle was builded, and the Altars appointed to be only there and it was a ſin for an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> of Gods People to offer any Sacrifice elſewhere, <hi>Levit.</hi> 17. 1, 2, 3, 4, 5. ſo that no Miniſter or Prieſt of God then was to perform any Church ordinance elſewhere, while the Tabernacle did continue (unleſſe they had a call immediately from God) ſo after in the Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple when it was builded, there were all <hi>Iſraell</hi> to bring their Sacrifice, there were the Miniſters to wait on the Altar.</p>
            <p>So likewiſe whatſoever was written afore time was written for our learning, <hi>Rom. 15. 4. Jeſus Chriſt the ſame yeſterday, and to day, and for ever,</hi> That we <hi>Be not carried about with divers and ſtrang doctrines,</hi> He. 13. 8, 9 We are then ſtill to obſerv the order of God, who at firſt ſent extraordinary men to publiſh his meſſage, and perform his ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and the Apoſtles before the Church was eſtabliſhed in Goſpel order, and they performed the ordinance of Baptiſm, wherſoever they preached and perſons believed: but when by theſe wiſe Maſter builders, the Apoſtles, the Churches were planted, and the Tabernacle of God was with men, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 3. and 13. 6. and extraordinary Officers ceaſed, and ordinary Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers choſen by the Churches only remained, [An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable to the Prieſts or Miniſters of old in the
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:106057:20"/> Tabernacle or Temple:] where they were appoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to feed the Church of God, as it is written in <hi>Acts</hi> 20. 28. ſo that ſince extraordinary Officers are ceaſed, as Apoſtles and the like, and now none remain but Paſtors, Teachers, Elders, Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons and Relievers: which have no Authority to preſume to that Commiſſion, given only to the Apoſtles, <hi>Mat.</hi> 28. as go teach all Nations bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing them, but obſerve the latter words of Chriſt to them: <hi>ver.</hi> 20. teaching them (that they had planted in Goſpel order) to obſerve all things whatſoever I command you, accordingly the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> gave direction to the Churches<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſaying, As I have received of the Lord that which I deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered unto you, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. 1. ſo we ought to be followers of him as he was of Chriſt, accordingly he wrote to <hi>Titus,</hi> to ordain Elders, as (ſaith he) I have commanded thee, <hi>Titus</hi> 1. 5. and ſay to <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chippus,</hi> take heed to thy miniſtery which thou haſt received in the Lord that thou fulfill it, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>Col.</hi> 4. 16. and ſo God will be with his People to the end of the world, who follow his commands from the hands of the Apoſtles, but ſome preſumed in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their Commiſſion to be Apoſtles, but being tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed were found lyers, <hi>Rev.</hi> 2. 1. and ſuch were <hi>Falſe Apoſtles, deceitfull workers, transforming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into the Apoſtles of Chriſt,</hi> 2 Cor. 11. 13. And I fear there are two many ſuch falſe Apoſtles now a dayes.</p>
            <p>So that I know no Rule from the written Word of God for any Officer, as Paſtor or Teacher to perform either the ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm or the Lords Supper out of the Stative, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregative, Corporative Church or Body of Chriſt where they are choſen to attend.</p>
            <pb n="37" facs="tcp:106057:20"/>
            <p>Moreover I do not find in the written Word of God that any did perform the ordinance of Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Water, or the Lords Supper, but either they had an extraordinary call from God, as <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and the Apoſtles; or Ordinary, called by the Church thereunto by Office; ſo that ſeeing ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinary Officers and Offices are ceaſed, and only the ordinary remain, I know no Rule from Gods Word, that any Officer choſen of the Church can perform any Church Ordinance out of the Stative Aſſembly or Corporation, any more than a Juſtice, Conſtable, or Boſholder have any power by virtue of their Office to perform it out of the limits ſet them, by thoſe who choſe them into Office; ſo that not only the Authority is gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven them, but the limits is ſet them, how far it reacheth, and if they go beyond the bounds ſet them, (by a greater authority) they break order and are tranſgreſſors and none ought to obey them, and they lyable to be puniſhed by the King.</p>
            <p>Even ſo in Chriſts Kingdom and City, the Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers thereof are not to go beyond their limits, ſet them by the King of Kings, and becauſe ſome preſumed to break the order of God, <hi>as Corah, Dathan,</hi> and <hi>Abiram,</hi> Numb. 16. and <hi>Nadab</hi> and <hi>Abihu,</hi> Levit. 10. and <hi>Uzah,</hi> 1 Chro. 13. 9. 10. and <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>zziah,</hi> 2 Chro. 26. 18. Gods Judgment fell upon them, for preſuming to do Gods ſervice out of Gods order; even ſo in the dayes of the Goſpel ſome preſumed (as aforeſaid) to be Apoſtles, but were found lyers and miniſters of Sathan, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 11. And though <hi>Uzah</hi> was a Levite, yet he muſt not touch any of the holy things, which belonged only to the ſons of <hi>Aarons</hi> line, <hi>Numb.</hi> 4. 15. And the Lord <hi>ſmote the men of</hi> Bethſhemoth (<hi>becauſe
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:106057:21"/> they looked into the holy things in the Ark) fifty thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand threeſcore and ten men, Sam.</hi> 6. 19 So that let all know that as of old God was the God of Order: he is the ſame in all Churches of the Saints, 1 <hi>Cor. 14. 4. Col.</hi> 2. 5. So that the place where Baptiſm ought to be performed muſt be in the Stative Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly or Church of God, in which Aſſembly the ordinary Officers of Chriſts true Church ought only to perform, and thoſe who are not Officers of a true Church, have no Rule from the Word of God, either to baptize or adminiſter the Lords Supper, but if any out of Office preſume to do it, is accurſed as <hi>Corah, Uza</hi> and <hi>Uzziah,</hi> and as I heard ſome ſay, ſome of your Judgment have taught perſons muſt be dipt or damned, If this be ſo, it is very high judging, <hi>Mat.</hi> 7. 1. We find it written, <hi>He that believeth and is baptized, ſhall be ſaved, and he that believeth not, ſhall be damned,</hi> Mark 16. 16. The ſtreſs of damnation is for not believing, the Holy Ghoſt foreſeeing that in the greateſt heat of perſecution, men by reading holy Scriptures may believ: &amp; ſeeing none have right to baptize, but the Miniſters of a true Church, and when the Church cannot of a Soul be fond, and die in that time, who dare ſay, that Soul ſhall not be ſaved as it is written, tell me, O thou, whom my Soul loveth, where thou feedeſt, and where thou makeſt thy Flock to reſt at noon? For why ſhould I be as one that turneth aſide by the Flocks of thy Companions, <hi>Cant.</hi> 1. 7. Here was no neglect of the Souls deſire to give it ſelf up in holy Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nant with Chriſt and his Church, when it ſaw the true way of God, <hi>Deut. 26. 17, 18, 19. Ruth</hi> 1. 16. and 2. 12. 2 <hi>Cor. 11. 2. Jer.</hi> 50. 5. to put in pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctice Gods holy Ordinances, <hi>Mat. 7. 24. James</hi>
               <pb n="39" facs="tcp:106057:21"/> 1, 22, 23. for the neglect of injoying or perform<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Gods holy Ordinance is a ſin: but it ſhall not be laid to their charge, if they want the injoyment of Gods Ordinances, when in Gods holy Order they cannot have it: but what will belaid to their charge, that ſhall run head-long upon the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Chriſt with out warrant from his Word?</p>
            <p>Secondly, Next I ſhall now ſhew on what part of the Body Baptiſm of Water, ought to be adminiſtred, or is moſt likely by the Scriptures, it was adminiſtred upon.</p>
            <p>You have <hi>R. A.</hi> ſuppoſed becauſe they went down into the Water, that therefore they were dipt, do you think one cannot go into the water, unleſs he be over the head. Conſider my friend a man is ſaid to be in the mountain, when he ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth within the limits of it, <hi>Mat. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 1. 2 Pet. 1. 8. Deut. 10. 1. Heb.</hi> 12. 20. Chriſt is ſaid when he was teaching in a Ship, that he ſat in the Sea, <hi>Mark</hi> 4. 1. So that when one is never ſo little in the water, it anſwereth to the going into the water, but it is very likely <hi>John</hi> preaching in the Wilder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs where the River was, which by reaſon of Ebbing and Flowing of the Water (as <hi>Enon</hi> and <hi>Jordan</hi> were great Rivers joyning to the Sea) might at ſides be muddy, and in the Wilderneſs having nothing conveniently to take up water, they might that were baptized go ſo far as to take with the hand, clear water to caſt upon the face, or forehead; for the dumb beaſt will go ſo far into the River to drink, as he may have clear water, much more a man being a reaſonable crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, will go ſo far as to have clear water to caſt upon the face or forehead, leſt the eyes be filled with dirt being ſo tender a place, God having ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointed
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:106057:22"/> every ordinance for the good of his people and not for their hurt: and as I ſaid before how Jeruſalem <hi>and all</hi> Judea, <hi>and all the Regions round about</hi> Jordan, <hi>were baptized of</hi> John, when here a part muſt be taken for the whole: Becauſe <hi>The Phariſees and Lawyers rejected the counſell of God a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt themſelves, being baptized of</hi> John, <hi>Luke</hi> 7. 30. and theſe were inhabitants of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> John 1. 19. 24. So that here a part is taken for the whole, in like manner we may conclude, the uſe of water in Baptiſm on a part of the Body, even the Face or forehead which repreſenteth the whole Perſon.</p>
            <p>As for example, <hi>Hagar</hi> was ſaid to flee from the Face of her Miſtris, which was from her per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, <hi>Gen.</hi> 16. 6, 8. for farther evidence ſee theſe Scriptures, <hi>Lev. 19. 23. 2 John ver. 12. 3 John 8. 14. Rev.</hi> 6. 16. and many ſuch like teſtimonies there is.</p>
            <p>Likewiſe, when <hi>Iſraell</hi> played the Harlot, ſhe is ſaid to have a whores forehead, ſetting forth all her abominations by the forehead. beheld of all, and yet not aſhamed, <hi>Jer.</hi> 3. 3. So the falſ Church hath upon her forehead a name written <hi>Myſtery,</hi> Babilon <hi>the Great, the Mother of Harlots, and Abo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minations of the Earth,</hi> Rev. 17. 5.</p>
            <p>Moreover the Saints are not aſhamed of the profeſſion of the Goſpel, <hi>Rom.</hi> 1. 16. ſignified as ſealed on the forehead, <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 3. departing from all iniquity as a ſeal to Gods people, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 2. 29. So that as Baptiſm of Water is a manifeſting of Chriſt to <hi>Iſraell,</hi> John 1. 31. a ſign of Remiſſion of Sins by Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 2. 38. whereon ſhould it be adminiſtred but on that part of the Body, w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ic<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> rep<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>th the whole man, even the face
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:106057:22"/> or forehead, which place or part of man, the name of Chriſt is ſaid to be, <hi>Rev.</hi> 23. 4. whoſe name is the Word of God, the of Chriſt, <hi>Rev.</hi> 19. 13. the Covenant of the Goſpel, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10. where then ſhould the ſign, ſeal, or token be adminiſtred but to the Covenant, and on that place where the Covenant or Name of Chriſt is ſaid to be, even on the fore-head? <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 4.</p>
            <p>Again, Chriſts Law or Covenant is alſo ſaid, to be written in the mind and heart of his people, <hi>Heb.</hi> 8. 10. and the ſpirituall Baptiſm being there, for Chriſt dwelleth in the heart by faith, <hi>Eph.</hi> 3. even by the ſpirit of faith, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 4. 13. then it will neceſſarily follow, that as the inward bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm of Gods ſpirit, is adminiſtred by God him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf on that place, even the heart where his Law or Covenant is wrot: the end of the Commandment being love out of a pure heart and of a good con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience, and of faith unfained, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 5. ſo ought the outward baptiſm of water to be adminiſtred, on that place even the forehead, where Chriſts name or covenant is recorded, <hi>Rev.</hi> 22. 4.</p>
            <p>Moreover when the Lord ſent the Meſſenger to deſtroy the wicked in Jeruſalem, thoſe that were to be preſerved or ſaved, were marked on the forehead, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 9. So likewiſe in <hi>Rev.</hi> 7. 3. and as Baptiſm is a figure of our ſafety, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 3. 21. and the forehead or face repreſenteth the whole man; why not a part taken for the whole in this Ordinance as well as in the Spiritual Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſm, and the mark of old, and now of the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple of God, <hi>Ezek. 9. Rev.</hi> 7. in the forehead: a part was taken for the whole, as may be ſeen in the uſe of water, where Chriſt waſhed the Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples feet, as if the whole body had been waſhed,
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:106057:23"/> 
               <hi>John</hi> 13. ſignifying a cleanſing of the whole; ſo Baptiſm on the face or forehead ſignifyeth the whole body waſhed in the Blood of Chriſt, as a cleanſing from all ſins, for of old in the figures of cleanſing or ſanctifying, it was chiefly by ſprink<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling, a part taken for the whole.</p>
            <p>Again, If you will not grant a part to be ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken for the whole, we cannot juſtify the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures of truth, for it was ſaid, as <hi>Jonas</hi> was three dayes and three nights in the Whales belly, <hi>Ion.</hi> 1. 17. So ſhall the Son of Man be three dayes and three nights in the heart of the earth, <hi>Matth.</hi> 13. 40. But we know he lay but a part for the whole, therefore beware of following your own ſpirit, and have ſeen nothing, as the fooliſh Prophets did in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Prophecying out of their own hearts, <hi>Ezek.</hi> 13. and your having neither the warrant of the Learned to limit the word to one ſenſe of Dipping, neither the Scripture for your opinion, but take warning by the Counſel of the Holy Ghoſt, Curſed is he that addeth or dimini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſheth, which muſt needs be in denying the ſenſe and meaning of the Word.</p>
            <p>And next, I ſhall by the help of God ſhew you, that you are not faithful to practiſe what you ſeem to contend for in the adminiſtration of the Baptiſm of water, and that in your own Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are not yet Baptiſed, unleſs you grant a part to ſerve for the whole.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Philip</hi> and the Eunuch went down into the water, I ſuppoſe you will not deny, but ſo far as they both went into the water, was no part of Baptiſm, and when they were both gone ſo far into the water as was convenient to make uſe of the water, then <hi>Philip</hi> Baptiſed the Eunuch. Now
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:106057:23"/> whether <hi>Philip</hi> and the Eunuch went but to the ankles, or midleg, or knees, or waſt, before he Baptiſed the Eunuch, is not mentioned in the Text, the Scripture is ſilent; but according to your Judgment, that the whole body muſt be dipt, or elſe none are Baptiſed, then ſure you muſt prove that the Eunuch was born up in the arms of <hi>Philip</hi> quite out of the water, and ſo dipt all the body under water, or elſe ſo far as the Eu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuch went he Baptiſed himſelf, or elſe <hi>Philip</hi> put the reſt of the body of the Eunuch that was out of the water in the water, and ſo <hi>Philip</hi> Baptiſed but a part for the whole; and as I am informed by ſome that have ſeen the manner of your Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtration o<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> Baptiſm, that the party that is to be Baptiſed goeth into he water with the Admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſtrator to the Loyns, and the Adminiſtrator putteth the other part of his body which is out of the water into the water, and ſo you Baptiſe but a part for the whole, yet you plead for dipping the whole body, and yet practice the contrary; ſuppoſing there is a m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#MURP" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>h in anothers eye, and the beam is in your own, and keep ado with that Scripture, <hi>Rom. 6. Buried with Chriſt in Baptiſm:</hi> and that of 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15. 29. Baptiſed for dead, or for the dead, anſwerable to a mans burial that is dead and put in the ground: But if you will practiſe what you contend for (as I ſaid before) the Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſtrator muſt bear up the man that is to be Baptiſed quite out of the water, and ſo put him into the water, as a dead man into the Grave; but did you ever know a man that was dead bury himſelf to the knees or waſte, and ſome other bury the reſt of the mans body? to ſee this would be a Miracle. But a man cannot by any Rule
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:106057:24"/> from Gods word Baptiſe himſelf, neither a part nor whole; but ſo far as you go into the water, you do Baptiſe your ſelves, and another Bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth the reſt; thus you muſt acknowledg a part is by you practiſed for the whole, or elſe in your own Judgment you are yet unbaptiſed, and yet condemn others that believe and practiſe a part for the whole, on that part of the body that re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth a part for the whole, even the Fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head, or Face: And now I will ſhew you by the teſtimony of four ſeveral writers, who was the beginner of your manner of Baptiſm by Dipping of himſelf, though before this time there might be ſome that held your Judgment, but knew not of any true adminiſtrator by ſucceſſion; but one being more deſperately wicked than others, would begin to Baptiſe himſelf, and others being deceived by him, follow after; but beware and follow not a multitude to do evil, <hi>Exod.</hi> 23. 2.</p>
            <p>In the dayes of King <hi>James,</hi> or thereabouts, one Mr. <hi>Smith,</hi> who was of the Church of <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> after diſliking thereof, and leaving <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gland,</hi> in proceſs of time was admitted a Member of a people of our Judgment, then living in <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterdam,</hi> commonly, but falſly called <hi>Browniſts;</hi> and in proceſs of time was caſt out of that Church for Errors he held; and not long after he fell to deny his Baptiſm in infancy, and knew not how to have a better, nor a truer Adminiſtrator ſuc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſively after your way of Dipping; at length he Baptiſed himſelf, and then he Baptiſed one <hi>Helviſh</hi> by name; this you may ſee in a Book written by one Mr. <hi>Jeſſop,</hi> preſented to King <hi>James:</hi> more to <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>his purpoſe I have ſeen in a book written by Mr. <hi>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>obinſon</hi> living then at <hi>Leyden</hi> in
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:106057:24"/> 
               <hi>Holland;</hi> alſo in another Book written by one Mr. <hi>Clifton,</hi> who wrote an anſwer to one of Mr. <hi>Smiths</hi> Books; and in another Book written by Mr. <hi>Henry Ainſworth,</hi> Teacher at that time in the Church where Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> was caſt out from, and as I have heard when I lived in <hi>London,</hi> that one <note n="*" place="margin">This of Mr. <hi>Spilſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bury</hi> I ſpeak as I was told, the others teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony is publick in Print, and ſuch men as were worthy to be believed<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </note> Mr. <hi>Spilsbury</hi> ſhould go to <hi>Holland</hi> to be Baptiſed of this <hi>Smith,</hi> ſo he brought it into <hi>England:</hi> And if you can prove no better an Adminiſtrator, your Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry will be found to come out of the bottomleſs pit, as <hi>Romes</hi> Miniſtry did: And that you may know how near kin your Baptiſm is to <hi>Romes,</hi> I ſhall lay down their man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, as their own Writers ſay, It is a dipping three times in water, <hi>In the Name of the Father, and of the Son, and of the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> in <hi>Bellarm. de ſac. Bap. 1. 1. c. 25. Bellarm. de Image 1. 2. c.</hi> 29.</p>
            <p>Again, conſider my friend, ſuppoſe a man while he is an unbeliever, in the Wars have a leg or arm ſhot off, and yet by Chyrurgery he is cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, that he is as heart-whole as ever, and may probably live as long as if that had not befallen him, and in proceſs of time comes to be a Belie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, ſhall not this man be Baptiſed (if he was not Baptiſed before) becauſe you cannot Baptiſe all the whole man, having not all his Members, <hi>As many members make one body,</hi> 1 Cor. 12. and this man with his heart believeth, and with his mouth confeſſion is made to Salvation, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10. Shall not this man be Baptiſed think you; and here a part muſt be taken for the whole, or elſe it is not
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:106057:25"/> lawful to Baptiſe ſome Believers contrary to the Scriptures.</p>
            <p>And again, If the Baptiſm be utterly denyed not to be retained which we have received in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtate Churches, you thereby affirm all the peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple that are in our known parts of the world, to be unbaptiſed, and you cannot prove a ſucceſſion in your way, and ſo no lawful miniſtry to Bap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe a People, for no unbaptiſed perſon may be a Miniſter to Baptiſe (but ſuch was Mr. <hi>Smith</hi> in his own judgment). Neither have any unbap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſed people power to elect or ordain a Miniſter among them; of this can no rule, preſident, or example be ſhewed in the Scripture, but all to the contrary, eſpecially ſince all extraordinary Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers have ceaſed; So muſt all the building of Chriſts Church, and work of the Miniſtry ceaſe, until ſome ſecond <hi>John Baptiſt,</hi> or new Apoſtles be ſent down from Heaven, &amp;c. And they that make a new Miniſtry (as <hi>Jeroboam</hi> did, will be found to be the worſhip of the Devil, and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Sathan, 2 <hi>Chron. 11. 15. 2 Cor.</hi> 11. falſe Apoſtles, deceitful workmen) muſt alſo make a new Goſpel, and confirm it with new Miracles, as I have heard ſome ſay, when they could not prove a ſucceſſion of Dipping by a trùe Miniſtry, from the Apoſtles dayes, they have thought an unbaptiſed perſon might begin the work, to Baptiſe by Dipping, but for warrant hereof, no one word of God could be brought; as <hi>Iſrael</hi> who made them Idols after their own underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, <hi>Hoſ.</hi> 13. 1-3. When <hi>the way of man is not in himſelf, it is not in man that walketh to direct his ſteps, Jer.</hi> 10. 23. but that we may beware of the Rocks of Popery, and quick-ſands of Anabapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:106057:25"/> by the light of God's Word, let us conſider what is the ſafeſt way to take in this diſtreſs; when men are at their wits end, whither ſhould we go, but to the Lord for counſel? <hi>Iſa.</hi> 42. 16, God's gracious Spirit blowing upon the ſails of our faith, we ſhall ſafely ſail through all theſe dif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficulties, into a ſtrait way to the ſincere practiſe of the Goſpel; for he that hath aſcended up on high, hath not left his Church deſtitute of coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, in all times and eſtates whatſoever; and though the Lord, for the judgment of the world, and trial of his ſervants, and manifeſtation of his power, bring his ſervants into <hi>Babylon,</hi> yet knoweth he how to deliver his ſervants, without juſtifying of Antichriſtian or <hi>Babylonian</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, to bring his people forth to <hi>Sion,</hi> and to rear up the decayed Tabernacles of <hi>David,</hi> which were fallen down, <hi>Amos</hi> 9. 11. without uſing one ſtone of <hi>Babel</hi> in the work for a corner, or for a foundation: And we being fallen into deep Apoſtaſie in theſe parts of the world, let us ſee whether we can find any preſident of ſuch times, and ſee whether we can fetch any better directi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons for the retaining of the Ordinance of Baptiſm, than your way of Anabaptiſtry, or twice bapti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zing; for it is good for all to obſerve, that the perſons which <hi>John Baptiſt</hi> and the Apoſtles did baptize, were not baptized before, as we were in the ſtate of Apoſtaſie.</p>
            <p>We read, That <hi>whatſoever things were written aforetime, were written for our inſtruction,</hi> Rom. 15. 4. And we find written in the time of <hi>Heze<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kiah,</hi> that the Kingdom of <hi>Iſrael</hi> had a long time remained in Schiſm and Apoſtaſie, having for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken the true Temple, and made to themſelves
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:106057:26"/> new Temples, new Altars, as the Hiſtory of the <hi>Chronicles</hi> do declare, 2 <hi>Chron</hi> 30. neither could by any warning be reclaimed; only ſuch as did re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn, and left their falſe worſhip, and came to the true Temple to worſhip God, were received and admitted to the Paſſeover, without either ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering, correcting or repeating the Circumciſion they had received in the times of their Apoſtacy. The like we read in the times of <hi>Joſiah,</hi> in 2 <hi>Chron.</hi> 30. and in <hi>Ezra</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah,</hi> when they had yet longer continued in their Schiſm and Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; and yet upon their return out of captivity unto the Lord, the Circumciſion then received was not repeated again, <hi>Ezra</hi> 6. 21, 22. yet no doubt, to thoſe men in thoſe times, while they continued in that idolatrous eſtate, the Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciſion then received, was no true ſeal of Gods Covenant to them, being added to their falſe Worſhip, Idolatry and Apoſtacy: And I think this will be granted of all hands, that God's Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant is no longer continued with any Church or people, than they remain in his faith and obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience, <hi>Rom.</hi> 2. 25.</p>
            <p>But ſome may ſay, I juſtifie the outward acti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Circumciſion, as it is done in the falſe Church; nothing leſs, but condemn it altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as a hainous profanation of God's holy Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinance; yet when it is purged by ſincere re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance of the abuſe thereof, it pleaſed God, in pardoning the faults; and to reſerve, and not re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the outward action; which becauſe it was vvrongly done, it cannot be ſaid not to be done at all, for vve muſt put a difference betvveen a thing not rightly done, and a thing not done at all; for the errors and defaults of the Baptiſm
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:106057:26"/> being purged by Repentance, and done away by the mercy of God; the Lord now beholdeth the reſt of the action, and the thing which in pretence they ſeemed to do, as his Ordinance; ſo that we find this way the way of God, concerning Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumciſion received in the falſe Church, when as thoſe perſons that were Circumciſed in that ſtate, and after came to the true way of God, they were not Circumciſed again; the like may be ſaid of Baptiſm, ſeeing Circumciſion was the ſeal of faith, and Baptiſm now, as is before proved. So by like equality, as the one Seal received in A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtacy and not repeted; ſo Baptiſm received in Apoſtacy, is not to be repeted; and ſo we have a foundation in Gods word to build our faith up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and not to follow your own ſpirits.</p>
            <p>Object. <hi>But if any ſay that Circumciſion could not be repeted again, and Baptiſm may, becauſe the fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>skin being once cut, could not after be cut again.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſw.</hi> The Apoſtle reſolveth this doubt, ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, <hi>If any man called being Circumciſed, let him not become uncircumciſed, 1 Cor.</hi> 7. 18. which words do import, that there might be a gathering of the fleſh again by the Art of Chyrurgery, as di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers Hiſtories do declare, <hi>Joſeph. Antiq. Lib. 12. chap.</hi> 6.</p>
            <p>And again, what ſhould be more againſt rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, to think why the outward Baptiſm delivered in a falſe Church, ſhould be denyed to be retain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, ſeeing Circumciſion that was received in a falſe Church was not denyed, when as the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures ſhew that the ſtate of the <hi>Romiſh</hi> and falſe Church in their Apoſtacy, is like the ſtate of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their Apoſtacy, as theſe and like Scriptures do ſhew, <hi>Rev.</hi> 17. 1. 5<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with <hi>Jer. 3. 8. Hoſ. 2. 2, 3. 1 Theſ.</hi> 2. 3.</p>
            <pb n="50" facs="tcp:106057:27"/>
            <p>Therefore Baptiſm received in ſuch eſtate is to be eſteemed; Now as Circumciſion was in <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael</hi> in their defection, but that Circumciſion was ſo eſteemed, and ſuch a ſtate and walking was only repented of. Thus if perſons will follow the preſident of Scripture, they ſhall find comfort at laſt; but for perſons to deny this Baptiſm, and own that true Baptiſm, for a man to Baptiſe him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf as <hi>Smith</hi> did, is proved by ſeveral teſtimonies, this will be their reward, as ſaith the Prophet, <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold all ye that kindle a fire, that compaſs your ſelves about with ſparks, walk in the light of your fire, and in the ſparks that ye have kindled, this ſhall ye have of mine hand, ye ſhall-lye down in ſorrow,</hi> Iſa. 50. 11.</p>
            <p>Thus according to my weak ability, in unfain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed love to your ſoul, I have returned you ſome Anſwer to your anſwer to <hi>John Turners</hi> Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment for Infants Baptiſm, though he himſelf, if he had pleaſed while he lived, could have given you a more fuller Anſwer; But foraſmuch as your deſire was I ſhould peruſe the writing between you, I was willing, for the vindication of the Truth of God in this point, though the unfitteſt of many; but as many of their great abilities brought rich things for the work of the Taberna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle, yet thoſe of ſmall abilities who brought but Goats hair, being accepted of God, was not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpiſed; ſo though my abilities be but ſmall to far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the work of the Lord, I hope it will not alto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether be deſpiſed of any that are imployed in the work of the Lords Tabernacle, the true Church of God, the ſtay and pillar of truth; thus deſiring the Lord to bleſs theſe my labours for the comfort of his Elect, and the Lord alone to have the glory, honour and praiſe, now and for evermore, <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="51" facs="tcp:106057:27"/>
            <p>Reader, I having no thoughts when I firſt wrote this Treatiſe, that it ſhould come to publick view, but ſeeing providence hath ſo diſpoſed thereof, I think good to acquaint thee, if theſe people which deny Infants Baptiſm, have like<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe deceived thee, as perſwading in word or writing, that it is not lawful to eat blood, and things ſtrangled, which is the Doctrine of Devils, 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4. For thy help againſt that error, you may have a ſmall Treatiſe where this book is to be had, proving it lawful, by the Doctrine of Chriſt and his Apoſtles, to eat blood and ſtrang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led things in theſe dayes of the Goſpel. Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed by the Author of this Book.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
